and we're live excellent so welcome back
everybody um we are now uh at the point
where we have reached the third keynote
lecture of main 2020 and it is my
distinct pleasure and honor uh to
introduce uh Professor Stanislas danan
from college the France in Paris um so
Professor danan is a professor on the of
chair of and experimental cognitive
psychology at the college the France in
Paris and he's director of the cognitive
neuroimaging unit at the or brain
Imaging Center um he received his
training in mathematics cognitive
psychology and neuromodeling uh
Professor Dan's interests concern the
cerebral basis of specifically human
cognitive functions such as language uh
computations calculations and reasoning
he has received several International
prizes I won't have time to list them
all here they include the MacDonald
Centennial Fellowship and the the Lou de
price for the French Academy of Sciences
with Danielle L um I could go on and on
um I can just tell you above all how
excited I am that um personally and also
the organizing Committee of Maine that
this is finally happen happening I mean
Stan probably remembers that I've been
bugging him with emails every year just
some months before Maine saying is it
gonna happen this year so finally it's
happening it's coming true we are um we
have now the chance to to listen to talk
keynote lecture by Stanislas danan in
Maine so without any further Ado uh
please join me in welcoming um Professor
danan for his talk that is entitled uh
Consciousness from computation to
cognition cognitive neuroscience and the
clinic so pleas hey hello thank you so
much for this nice introduction I hope
you can see my slides yes and um yeah I
wish I had accepted your invitation
years ago so I could be in Montreal
right now
but locked from my room I will try to
tell you a little bit about my thoughts
about Consciousness and a lot of new
data uh the plan of my talk is the
following first I will tell you about uh
some of the contents of this first book
consciousness and the brain and new data
to suggest that basically I think we
begin to understand the basic operation
of conscious access how we perceive
something in the external world we have
identified signatures of Consciousness
and we are progressing in this respect
they are shared between animals and uh
human and uh we are Guided by a theory
the global neuronal workspace Theory and
the data so far seem to converge rather
nicely um but in the second part of my
talk if I have enough time I would like
to tell you a little bit about new ideas
that I developed in the second book how
we learn and develop the second idea
that the contents of Consciousness may
be different in humans they're richer in
humans um we process a language of
thought which leads us to Unique
competencies for language for mass for
music conscious representation of
ourselves and others and uh we'll try to
show you therefore that these are
abilities that require specific models
um in terms of AI this is really a
neuroscience talk I think but here is
where AI is going to come in first of
all it's used as a tool in order to
decode brain signals and to classify
patients with disorders of Consciousness
based on the signatures of Consciousness
and second um it's used uh as a
potential model I think it's achievable
to model the global neuronal workspace
and we've just heard from Josh Benjo
about this but um I will also claim that
the current AI remains Limited in its
ability to capture human behavior and
propose some challenges that I think are
not met at least so as far as I know
from simple current neural network
approaches um so uh my talk will be uh
based on the Progressive development of
a theory of Consciousness which called
Global workspace Theory started with
this very nice book by G Bas which I can
still heavily recommend 1988 and then
Through The Years my colleagues and I
have been refining the theory and if you
want to read just one paper this I think
this recent paper in 2017 or maybe the
even more recent review uh with Peter
ruar George mure je sh will give you
some more details but to beef up the
idea I want to start with a very simple
visual illusion that I think many of you
know uh here you can see um some uh
check chess pieces is on the board and
there's a black piece and there's a
white piece and uh well where is the
illusion uh I think you know where it's
coming is that these uh bits of the
image are actually strictly identical
they're the same exact luminance I hope
you can see this now if I go back and
forth but we subjectively see them as
completely different and um what's going
on is that our brain unconsciously
detects that there's a sort of Shadow
sort of Gray Zone in the image subtracts
it and let us see the luminance of this
object as lighter because if it was in
the shadow it would have to be a lighter
color um what I like about this example
is that first of all I think it nicely
illustrates the notion that dates from
helmo that the visual system operates by
unconscious inference and what we see
consciously is really the result of a
lot of computation but also this is a
subjective illusion uh it's very clear
that we don't see the objective reality
which would be these grade here so it's
subjective and yet machine confronted
with the same display would have to to
come to the same conclusion if you're
really trying to see the objects on the
scene you have to subtract the Shadow
and so subjective Illusions are not at
all incompatible with even optimal
computations by a machine I think that's
what the brain does um so I will um use
two key ideas here the first one is that
there is a lot of early perceptual
processing which is unconscious
accumulates the evidence from the scene
combines it together and that conscious
perception relates to a later wave of
longer lasting neuronal activity that
integrates the incoming signals for
instance here it has to integrate the
knowledge of the Shadow and illuminance
in order uh to create more Global and
globally available information so this
is of course the idea of the global
neuronal workspace I've shown this
picture many times uh what's the idea
first of all that there are many chains
of processes in the brain cortical areas
are typically autonomous processes
neurons operate in parallel and all of
these chains can operate unconsciously
and there can be many such chains at a
given time but the second claim is that
what we subjectively experien as
Consciousness is the global availability
of information there are some chains the
green one here that end up in this high
level system for sharing information and
at this in turn they can contact other
processing chams link them together and
the idea is consciousness relates to the
activity of This Global neuronal
workspace that evolve to select a piece
of information from this chain for
instance here so to attend to it to
broadcast it to other systems leading to
a Global Knowledge inside the system and
the ability for instance to report
verbally the stimulus to act upon it to
memorize it and so on and so forth in
terms of physiology the hypothesis has
been that conscious access correspond to
the ignition of neurons with
longdistance connection you need these
long distance connections to broadcast
information that would be distributed in
prefrontal cortex and other associative
C cortex this is not a localist theory
of Consciousness but the idea that
prefontal cortex is just one of the
nodes here and that top down signals are
also being sent back to the processors
and I won't go through that but there's
more and more evidence for this notion
of a sort of central system a bottleneck
of multiple areas that speak to each
other very quickly and for instance in
the work of Henry Kennedy here from
anatomy of the mountain so what is
common to all conscious processing
States well not necessarily the same no
not a single state or a single marker or
NCC but more a processing style a type
of neural trajectory that involves this
broadcasting operation and so what are
the predictions of these models um I
speak mostly about the predictions about
the trajectories of conscious and
unconscious processes and that's why I
will be using in my Talk data mostly
from Meg and also neurophysiological
recordings rather than fmri because we
want the Dynamics so the Dynamics first
of all is that there should be
propagations of activity coming from
unconscious ston they may not reach
Consciousness but they can still proceed
along deep processing lines second
prediction there should be this sudden
Global ignition all of these areas come
together this create a nonlinearity in
the system Global amplification when a
novel content gains access to
Consciousness and uh this should be seen
at the level of prefrontal Cortex
neurons among others they should contain
this is a very strong prediction there
should be a complete neural code for any
conscious content at a given moment in
the prefontal cortex and related areas
there are two other predictions this is
a bottleneck so only a single
conscious object can make it at a given
time so if it's the green one it's not
the orange one for instance and there's
also the idea of spontanous ignition you
don't have to have an external stimula
it doesn't have to come from the outside
from the periphery it can come from
inside from memory from spontaneous
patterns of thought um but I won't have
time to cover all of these points so I
will focus on this of sudden Global
ignition coming after a series of
processing stages that are unconscious
we've been doing a lot of experiments
with this and uh the typical experiment
goes like this we will flash an object
for instance a digit here it's flash for
a very brief duration and then there is
a mask and the mask can come after a
variable delay which we vary here and if
the delay is very short you don't see
the stimulus and you don't even
distinguish it from Target absent trials
at threshold sometimes you can see it
some sometimes you don't and above
threshold typically after something like
60 70 milliseconds you can see the
stimulus and we've been chasing in the
brain the activation caused by such
stimuli this is an old experiment
already from 2007 only using EG and we
could see that there are indeed several
waves of processing what we could see
here is that if you record from visual
cortex you see a first wave which is
essentially linear in activation as a
function of the evidence provided by the
stimulus before being cuted by the mouse
so you can see evidence accumulation
here and then there's this second wave
which by the way is the only one which
is seeing very strongly here in the
prefrontal cortex following this sort of
slow buildup here there's this
nonlinearity in the system and here the
curves are separated much more
nonlinearly for instance if you can see
if you can focus on the green curve you
can see that a 33 millisecond stimulus
will create visual activation but then
it dies off and uh there is no second
wave here what we could see is that the
fraction of C
digits the subjective reports of the
subjects correlates with the size of
this late wave and we propose that this
is a possible signature of Consciousness
I just like to point that this division
between a linear phase and a nonlinear
ignition phase uh is present in many
many experiments and we have even been
able to use it to find that there is
such an organization in the baby the
baby cannot report but we can still see
that if you flash a phas for a short
duration this experiment was done by S
Creer um uh there is a linear variation
in the evoked potentials as a function
of phase duration here and then a
nonlinear stage where only the long
duration phases create this sustained
negativity whereas the short ones at
essentially Return To Zero so we believe
that there is ignition already in the
young baby uh at certainly at 12 months
we see so it very clearly and I think
this is the data from 12 months but
perhaps much earlier probably maybe even
very close to birth the earliest
evidence we had in this experiment was
at five
months so it's a basic architecture of
the system we can see it many times we
have a new tool now to look at these
things which is multivariate decoding
and this has been a very strong
contribution of je King who did his PhD
in the lab um what we can do is we can
take a slice of time coming from these
uh EG Nets or from the mg that you can
see here and using all of these sensors
and this slice of time we can try to
build the decoder for what the subject
has been presented with for instance
decoding which image he has seen is it a
face a house an object or a body part
and this is actual data showing that of
course before the stimulus you can't
decode after the stimulus there is a
period where you can't and then you can
decode the stimulus but what's great
about this is you can also use the
pattern of generalization across time to
illuminate the organization of the
system think about it if there's a chain
of processors that they each have a
specific code then you could train on a
given time
and you could decode at the same time
even with new data but you could not
decode at a different time because the
activation is gone onto a different code
but if there's a stable sustained
ignited code then you could train at a
given time and still generalize to a
different generalization time using
different data from a different time
point because the data is stable and
it's not just Theory because this is
what we see in the actual data so this
was the work of Sebastian Marti you can
see here when we flash a picture we do
see a sort of diagonal pattern of
decoding which means we change a given
time we can mostly decode at about the
same time and then the information moves
to another coding scheme but later in
time you can see this slate much more
stable pattern and I will outline it for
you here so you can see there this much
more Square pattern which means that the
neural activity has become stable in
time and we can decode it and it seems
in our hands that this diagonal phase
corresponds much more to non-conscious
processing and this more stable phase to
conscious processing
so one way to see this is to use this
decoding in this masking experiment so
here is our masking stimuli what we
decode here is just the presence of the
stimuli can we distinguish between a
stimulus which is present like the D
nine here and a stimulus where there was
no digit at all just the mask we can
make this distinction we can make it
even when the stimulus is extremely
short like 17 or 33 milliseconds here
and this is a subliminal stimulus below
the threshold so you can see that it
creates a whole pipeline of activation
but notice what happens when we cross
the threshold here there's is much more
intense activation building up and then
suddenly there's this intense Square
pattern stable pattern of activity which
if we simply take the same exact
stimulus and separate unseen thec trials
nicely separates uh these two categories
you can see that there's much more
stable activity on the scene case and
this has been proposed as a notion of
metastability it's not that the activity
is no longer changing it's still
changing but it's changing much more
slowly the system has reached a much
more stable state of activity which we
claim is associated with broadcasting um
je Remy has been replicating this
pattern many times initially our
experiments were criticized because we
were using symbolic digits so we did
them again with grids you can see here
and in this experiment also with a long
delay before the subject sees a probe
and has to decide whether the probe is
tilted left or right compared to the
target you have to make this Choice even
if you don't see it it's very
interesting that you can be above chance
so even after a long delay like this of
close to one second um you can still use
some of the subliminal information
provided by the Target but of course
you're much better when you cross the
threshold the information becomes much
more stable in your mind when we decode
this situation we see once again a sort
of diagonal pattern for the Unseen
trials here so we see a trajectory in
neural space and surprisingly we can
continue to decode the Unseen stimulus
for a long time but still you can see
that the non-conscious trial is evoking
decaying activity in blue the SE in
stimulus is evoking much more stable
activity sustains whole time and uh even
though it's not a perfect square it
continues to evolve through time it's
much more stable much more broader in
this Matrix compared to the more
diagonal pattern evolved by the Unseen
stim creating this difference here so
this is what we call ignition it's not
just a stable pattern and it's a stable
trajectory and this notion that
conscious and unconscious processing can
be seen as divergent Dynamic trajector
has been a point that has been made by
others for instance Mo salti also
B what they see here is the same as we
see the seen trials even for a fixed
constant stimulus the seen trials
diverge very quickly from The Unseen
trials if you measure the speed of
Divergence I saw this was a very clever
trck or just measure the speed with
which the magnetic fields the mg change
you can see that suddenly they start to
change very quickly for the seen trials
compared to the Unseen trials that's
what we call nonlinear
ignition um now can we go beyond this
simple observation of ignition to what
it does what's the
computation our idea with Jean REM and
we proposed that in his paper in 2014
very formally is that uh the computation
is one of the posterior think of my
original example you have to compute the
posterior distribution of light uh the
probability that this is white or dark
as oppos based on all of the information
on the seene so it's a perceptual
decision following a long unconscious
inference uh we wrote this sentence
which I still like what we call a
subjective report May simply be the
brain's best attempt at solving a
difficult perceptual decision problem
with myriads of potential classes each
with different costs and prior
probabilities that depend on the
subject's prior experience so the
subjective report is not random at all
subjective is a computation but a
computation of a posterior in order to
test this idea je and Gabriel did a very
recent experiment it's not published yet
but uh the idea is that we can
manipulate the evidence by masking but
in order to separate it better from the
posterior we can also manipulate the
prior so we have a masking Paradigm here
we flash a digit there's a mask we vary
the S SOA the delay between the digit
and the mask but we also vary the prior
here by having two blocks you can see
them here there's one block where most
of the trials are invisible because we
present all of these short duration
trials most of them are invisible and
your prior is that you're going to get a
trial where you don't see the stimulus
and then in another block we present
some of the same durations but also
longer durations so that the prior is
that you're going to see most of the TRS
and uh if you look at the behavioral
data this is sufficient shift as
predicted by the model the subjective
reports the the subjective reports of
seeing integrate the prior and shift uh
the second block towards more visibility
even though it's the same stimulus and
even though the objective discrimination
as predicted by the fact that this is
based on unconscious computation the
objective discrimination Remains the
Same if we look at what happens at the
mg level we once again replicate this
idea of a trajectory for unconscious
stimuli which gets broader uh for when
the stimulus is seen and if we contrast
unseen versus seen stimuli simply based
on this middle stimuli where the
stimulus is the same and one of these
durations here so for a fixed s SOA uh
we have this distinction between seen
and unseen stimul which creates this
region of significant difference here
amplification of the activation followed
by this very late metastable phase um
but now we can dissociate it from SOA
with can do multiple regression this is
what we what jean Remy did here to
predict the outcome of this detector for
present versus absent trials and we can
see that the early stages are dominated
by the SOA by the objective evidence the
duration of the stimulus before the mask
and uh this is the visibility the
subjective component whether the subject
declared that he could see it and we can
clearly see that these affects different
stages of processing what about the
prior we can also identify a modulation
by the block uh with which the subject
is confronted is it a visible block
where most of the trials are visible or
is it an invisible block and this prior
affects the entire trajectory of
processing but primarily affects the
beginning even prior to the presentation
of the stimulus as should be expected
perhaps from the term prior so this is
the key figure if we put together all of
these influences we can see the
successive effects of the prior of the
evidence and of the posterior the
visibility ratings um on uh the decoding
of the presence versus absence of the
stimulus and I hope you can see these
chains of processing which go uh through
time here each of these is a slice of
the decoding so this is a decoder
trained at 120 milliseconds to decide
whether there was there was or there was
not a stimulus and you can see that the
decoder is first influenced by the prior
then by the evidence and finally
converges to the posterior and we see
that multiple times I think this is
consistent with the idea of a chains of
chains of processes that all have the
same sort of computation the same style
of computation at different levels and
eventually when you reach the last level
here by 300 millisecond you're
completely dominated by the visibility
the subjective final posterior of the
subject now all of these Meg data is
very nice but as you can see I'm showing
it to you in decoding space we can also
do s modeling and we can see that
prefrontal cortex contributes to this
and this is a distributed response but
the best of course is to go to animal
research uh in order to be able to
pinpoint the neural bases of this
ignition and so uh we started doing this
first of all in collaboration with Peter
ruin in this recent science paper we had
a monkey model of a flash stimulus
Crossing or not crossing the threshold
so this the param was even simpler than
before we just flash a little bit of
light with a variable contrast and
sometimes there's no stimulus at all so
zero contrast and uh if the monkey sees
the stimulus he has to make a sad to the
item and if he doesn't see the stimulus
he has to make a sad to a fixed dot or
to report not seen and once again we
have Behavior which is characterized by
this by this nonlinear thresold function
there's a thresold contrast for a given
animal uh below which you don't perceive
the stimulus even though it's present
and above which becomes very easy to
perceive and there are some ambiguous
stimuli here so we could ask in monkeys
how does the firing of cells in V1 V4
and prefrontal cortex varies as a
function of seeing or not seeing
including for the first time here the
presence of a large number of Mis
stimuli that is to say stimuli that are
present there is a contrast on screen
but the animal reports not seeing them
and what we saw is very clear I think
you can see it by yourself the visual
areas V1 and V4 can cannot be the basis
of conscious perception because they can
be very strongly activated both by sinen
stimuli but also by Mis stimuli so it
doesn't really matter much to these
areas whether there has there's going to
be subjective perception of seeing or
not uh on the other hand the prefrontal
cortex as you can see here um ignites
whenever the monkey reports perceiving a
stimulus it does so on seen trials you
can see the green curve here um and it
also does so on false alarm trials where
there was no stimulus but the monkey
thought that there was a flash of light
and made this um most important I think
is the Divergence between the red curve
and the green curve here they're the
same stimuli but um in one case you
missed the stimulus the monkey uh
reports not seeing the stimulus and you
can see that there is what we call
failed ignition there is a beginning of
a wave reaching prefontal cortex but
then it converges to the low state which
corresponds to the one when the monkey
reports not seeing so we really have a
sort of dynamic system here diverging
between two possible States the high
State for the monkey reports yes I saw
the stemulus and a low State this is
just about reporting ver just not
reporting so is really sort of neural
correlate of signal detection Theory
here um but uh according to the theory
we should be able to go further than
that and really we should see that
there's a detailed neuronal code for the
consciously perceived contents and that
this has nothing to do with report it
should be seen even in no report
paradigms where the monkey doesn't have
to do anything so this has been a
beautiful work by FIS panagos first in
Nikos logothetis lab which really
pioneered all of this work on
Consciousness in monkeys and then now in
neurospin in our lab um so what he's
doing is using a no report Paradigm
binocular rivalry situation where the
nice trick is that if the rivaling
stimuli are grids and in one eye they're
moving up in the other eye they're
moving down the two stimuli rival so
even if you're a subject you're a human
subject you see one stimulus and then
you see the other they the stimulus is
constant but your subjective perception
alternates but you don't have to ask for
a report because you see it in the eye
movements the eyes track the visible the
visible stimulus and if you perceive
movement towards the the top of the
screen for instance you see slow
movement followed by nagus to return to
the initial position and then you know
that the subject is seeing the top
stemulus so using this trick FIS has
been able to show that there are neural
populations in the prefrontal cortex
that encode which stimulus the animal is
seeing even when there is no need to
report at all and in fact even when
there are no eye movements at all just
these uh states of the prefrontal cortex
switch and they switch in correspondence
with the perception of the animal
whether it's physical switches or
whether it's binocular rivalry and the
switches are purely in the head
uh purely subjective there is no no
switch in the actual stimulus now this
is just for up Motion versus downward
motion so you could argue this is a very
poor um contents of Consciousness the
contents of Consciousness should be much
richer than that so can we go to much
stimuli well that's what joim B and FIS
are doing at neurospin we have these
uter arrays that allow to record from
you know uh close to 100 neurons in the
ventrolateral cortex of the monkeys and
uh we can see what happens when you just
submit them to a passive viewing
Paradigm where they see an object and
can we use uh the firings of the cells
in prefrontal cortex to decode what the
monkey is seeing well yes we can and not
only that but we can decode every single
picture that he is seeing out of a large
set of pictures such as 10 or 15 so
there is a neural Vector that suffices
to provide a lot of information compared
to chance about the identity of the
picture and we can decode each of the
successive pictures even in a relatively
fast tram where the subjective
impression is that there is a very
fleeting view of the image if you're
just submitted to this as a human
subject you say well I can see almost
every picture they are going very very
fast they keep changing each other what
we see in the prefrontal cortex if we
look at the decoding matrices is this
sort of very short diagonal followed uh
by cutting by the next stimulus so for
the last stimulus you can see there is
longer decoding and the Matrix is
actually longer and leads to this more
stable State here but we also have the
same state this is the same decoder in
the horizontal slice here so the same
brain state allows to decode the
identity of the picture only for a
shorter duration when the picture has
been presented inside this visual stream
of 10 pictures per second or rather five
pictures in half a second so what that
means is that this fleeting impression
of seeing a picture has a correlate in
the prefrontal cortex which can be
decorated
um of course what would be nice would be
to be able to ask the monkey to hang on
to one of these pictures here is just
pass of these pictures flash by and you
can sort of briefly see them what would
happen if we had to select a picture
hang on to it and report it later it's
very hard to train in a monkey maybe we
will be able to do that later but we did
that in a human again with Sebastian
Marti and uh so this is the Paradigm you
can see all of these pictures being
flashed one after the other in this case
there's nine pictures per second it's a
long screen of 12 images um and uh we
present a green frame around one of the
picture and the subject has to decide
what was the identity of this picture
keep it in mind keep it in the global
workspace because you have to decide
among all of the possible pictures which
one you saw when we do this we can build
a decoder based on Independent data
where the pictures are presented alone
this is what I showed you earlier we can
build a decoder for which picture is
being presented is it a face is it a
house is it a body part or is it an
object but then we can apply this
decoder to the stream of pictures and
the result is similar to the monkey
result I showed you earlier we see these
streams of decoding we see this decoders
that for a certain duration of time um
are able to detect what was the identity
of the image one then the image two then
image three and so on so forth coded by
color here so I insist that one
orizontal line through this graph is one
decoder but the decoder spits out a
different answer that corresponds to the
image number one then the image number
two then the image number three and
later in time you can get another
decoder that decodes the the subsequent
image so an interesting aspect of this
data is if you take a vertical slice
through the data here you have the same
exact data point but it can be decoded
in different ways if you capture the
early activity you're decoding the image
let's say number seven but if with the
same data use a different decoder you
might be capturing the image six or the
image five you're capturing the previous
images so we we must have this idea of a
brain which is constantly crisscrossed
by these bottom of perceptions coming
into the system and reaching into
prefrontal cortex now what happens when
one of them is a target so now we can
make the same exact decoders for Target
versus non-targets and what's the
difference well we see essentially two
differences there is an amplification of
the late activity just like you should
have expected from the previous
experiment I showed you uh the target is
held for a longer duration so now we're
reaching 500 600 milliseconds and you
can still decode the the the target you
can no longer decode the non-target here
and at the same time there is an
amplification of an earlier decoder
around 170 millisecond which used to
tell you what was the image but now
becomes Amplified the second time at the
same time as the top so this is probably
top down amplification what's very
interesting is that these two decoders
decode slightly different things the
late one decodes just the identity of
the picture which is your Target and
when a subject makes an error it decodes
the error but it's really amplifying one
particular item it's discrete all or non
selection correlated with subjective
reports so we think that this
corresponds to the access to the global
workspace the conscious report of one
particular item and the others you
forget but at this earlier time you see
that there is partial and gradual
selection there are several candidates
that's normal because there are as I
told you at a given slice of time here
there are many possible candidates in
the early visual areas you have one
picture but in the later areas you have
the previous picture in this pipeline so
this earlier um activation corresponds
to several potential candidates but at
the later stage here there's only one is
being selected and that can enter This
Global workspace and be report so I
think this characterize a little bit the
architecture of the system pipelines of
unconscious processing making infuences
and then a single selection
system
um I want to move to an auditory
Paradigm to tell you that the contents
of Consciousness can be even richer than
what I described to you already um
because of course it doesn't have to be
visual it could be auditory but also in
the auditory domain it's not just about
the identity of the stimulus but it's
also about the organization in time and
we've used this local Global auditory
novelty parano to investigate the
representation of stimuli through time
so um I hope you will be able to listen
to the
[Laughter]
stimulus okay so this is our basic
Paradigm we have you listen to a
sequence of sounds and in this case the
last one is different
and this will generate mismatch
responses in your brain the soal
mismatch negativity and the p300 waves
you are surpris then you attend to the
stimulus because there is a surprise
here but then we adapt we adapt you to
hearing this Global sequence of five
sounds Bo and we do that several times
and at the end you still get the
mismatch negativity but you lose the P3
this is what we call local novelty alone
globally you expect the entire sequence
of course your early unconscious
processor still detect that there's a
change of tone but that's expected
consciously and now what happens is that
if we present you a monotonic sequence
of tones that's when you react and you
say oh I'm surprised there is a global
surprise the sequence is not the one I
expected so in this way we can
dissociate the local transition
probability from the global surprise we
can have two levels of Errors if you
want and in this case the error is that
there is no error okay so it's a
hierarchical error process processing
paradig we can view it in this way this
is the full design where there's one
block where this is the base stimuli and
this is the surprise and there's another
block where the base stimul is monotonic
and this is the surprise so we
dissociate local surprise from Global
surprise now when we do this we find two
completely different types of
computations on top here you see the
local effect local in time as well as in
space it's a very fast response it's
this mismatch response it primarily sits
in the auditory cortex although there's
also a little bit of prefrontal Cortex
ability activation it's very sharp
response you can see it in intracranial
recording you see the first four sounds
they habituate they become smaller and
then suddenly you recover this very high
activation even bigger than the
beginning for the Deviant SS and it's a
completely diagonal pattern of decoding
which means it's a sequence of sharp
processing steps for this stimulus and
we find it can be completely unconscious
you can keep that even if you don't
attend if you asleep if you're in
you may still have it the global effects
completely different is distributed in
the space of the cortex it's much slower
typically after 300 millisecond 200 300
millisecond and it creates this very
broad decoding ability it's a sustain
state if you decode it at a given time
you can see it at lat
times and we've seen that this one
disappears on the unconscious situation
we've explored a lot this Paradigm to
show this dissociation between the local
unconscious versus global conscious
response and we've we've done it in the
monkey as well this has been done by B
Jara and Lin URI in the lab we've been
able to do fmri with the monkey to see
that there is a global workspace in the
monkey as well there's this distributed
system of areas that come up only for
the Global Response and in recent re
research we've seen that the Global
Response tend to disappear suddenly
during anesthesia when we fall asleep
regardless of the type of anesthetic and
will reappear and this is perhaps the
most interesting aspect from a clinical
point of view it will reappear if we
stimulate uh using deep electrodes the
central medial nucleus of the thalamus
this is still unpublished work by Jordi
tasi I hope soon to be published so what
we have here is a system that is
essentially a reflection a signature of
Consciousness if you have this novelty
response at this high level of
processing which integrate all of the
five sounds together to say you know
this is my expected Melody and it's been
violated then uh this is a conscious
level of processing and you only get
this response if the animal is conscious
now now that we have this param we can
go back to our electrodes and ask what
is being coded uh in the prefrontal
cortex of the monkey should can we see
these Global responses can we see a code
for the for what the monkey is seeing so
you know that with these U arrays we can
see several single neurons and uh this
setup has been provided by F Panago te
and this is the beautiful work of Mari B
here so what what do we see here first
of all we see that we can decode from
prefrontal cortex neurons the identity
of every object in a sequence we've
moved to a visual presentation because
we record more neurons that respond to
Vision in the monkey but this is a small
difference so bear with me so we can see
the identity of the stimuli here blue
blue blue blue orange orange orange
orange Etc we can decode the identity of
the stimulus I've already told you this
so if the last item is different well we
can decode that the identity of the
object has changed but in fact we can
decode every single bit of knowledge
that the monkey has of the sequence and
that's exactly what I told you at the
beginning there should be a code in the
prefrontal cortex for every single bit
of information that the monkey has every
single bit of conscious information so I
told you we can decode which picture
just appeared is it picture a or picture
B um this is running blocks so you can
get decoding even before the stimulus
appears but of course it gets Amplified
and we don't have to run this
experiments in blcks we can decode
identity but we can also decode the
ordinal position there's something
clicking in the monkey's head and in our
head when we go through the stimulus
that says well this is the first sound
this is the second sound this is the
third sound and when it comes to the
fourth sound maybe I should expect
something different uh because it's the
end of the sequence and I know it's
going to end differently so we can see
this we can see neural codes that have
first been described by Andreas nether
that care about the ordinal position of
the St um because we don't vary the SOA
for the moment and it is again
unpublished data we cannot really tell
whether this is number of time but we
think it's a mixture of both and also
some notion of first and last in the
sequence you can see item one item two
it three four there's a mixture of
identity information and ordinal
position information that tells you
where you are in the sequence and then
there's much more than that there is is
the last item different if the last item
is different Fates disuse mismatch
response which can be seen in prefrontal
cortex and of course the monkey knows
consciously uh that the last item is
different and uh interestingly we also
see this numerical response here you can
see something that says oh it's like the
first item it's like a new group of one
this light item is different so it's a
little bit like one okay um we can also
decode the global deviant so we have
other neurons that allow us to build
this decoder here which is expectedly
slower in time and tells us did I just
hear an unexpected sequence I expected
that it should end with a different
sound and it didn't so I get this Global
Response here so there's something in
the prefontal cortex that says I'm
surprised I should work more and what's
very interesting is we even find neurons
that before the onset of the sequence
and code what should I expect the monkey
knows as we know in this Paradigm that
he is in a block where it should end
with a different sounds so we can decode
that from the beginning from specific
cortico populations so all of these
neurons are intermixed together we can
think of prefrontal Cortex as having
multiple vectors that each code for
these dimensions of experience but the
entirety of experience is reflected in
prefontal cortex and I insist that this
is in a non-reporting mon there is no
report here just passive listening to
these
sequences so I promise to go very
quickly to the clinic just to say that
this local versus Global Response is
just one of the tools that we have Curr
in the clinic uh to decide whether to
help decide whether a person is or is no
longer conscious there is very difficult
uh clinical problem of deciding whether
someone with in a vegetative state or
minimal Consciousness So-Cal unw sorry
vegetative state is now unresponsive
wakefulness syndrome uws here or minimal
Consciousness MC how do we decide it
seems that some of these patients in
apparent vegetative state are actually
still conscious where we can have them
listen to this Paradigm and as shown by
jacobo this is one indication that they
might still be conscious if they still
get this Global Response the local
response we know we can get from comos
patients it's not the only tool and from
Global workspace Theory we have several
additional tools we can simply look at
the amount of sharing of information
especially in the Theta band here in the
long distances of the cortex the more
there is sharing of information the more
likely the patient is to be conscious
and we can also look at fmri and this is
something I won't have time to describe
at all but just the resting state
activity in fmri has become a very
interesting cue to the state of the
subject is if there is variation in the
resting state activity as you can see
these matrices of functional
connectivity varying through time then
there is the high likelihood that the
patient is conscious this is a signature
that we found in the monkey first and
translate to the human so by combining
these signatures we can begin to have
automatic classifiers of patients
um using multiple EG markers uh we can
classify much better than chance whether
a patient is or is not still conscious I
will not have time to describe all of
the specific measures here but from a
clinical point of view it does not
matter of course it matters from the
theory what are these signatures but
from the clinic the important thing is
that we can begin to help classify these
patients better and very interestingly
inside the vegetative state it seems
that uh we don't always agree with the
clinical classification which is
provided by the doctor the classifier
the machine learning may not agree and
in fact the machine perhaps predicts
better at least sometimes because a
greater number of patients that are
classified as being conscious tend to
recover as opposed to not improving so
there is also a pronostic value from
some of these markers this has become
quite an industry of decoding of these
patients it's all done in the laboratory
of lonel Nash and in this paper putting
together a lot of data from different
groups we show that using random Forest
algorithm we can get robust EG decoding
uh and what's important is that it is
cross sight now so from different
clinical sites maybe using different EG
machines we can begin to have a common
classifier in the last part of my talk
and it will have to be necessarily a bit
short um I would like to
uh move to this theme that I mentioned
at the beginning do we all have the same
contents of Consciousness I hope I've
shown you that from makak to human we
have similar mechanisms of access to
Consciousness when we perceive a line or
when we perceive motion or perhaps a
face the mechanisms are very very
similar and we have this nonlinear
access to Consciousness but my
hypothesis is that there is something
different in a human when it comes to
higher level States we have richer
States we are able to represent
information in a deeper manner in this
review in the journal neuron we
discussed the representation of
sequences with this idea coming from
this local Global Paradigm that sequence
knowledge is already present in the
monkey and of course the monkey already
knows about the transitions between the
items and knows that there's one which
can be expected I've shown you this
other experiments show that the monkey
can group the items together into chunks
the monkeys also know about the order of
items this is the first this is the
second this is the third I've shown you
that and the monkeys may even be able to
learn an algebraic pattern so the first
two are identical for instance a a b a a
and then there is perhaps a violation of
this pattern all of this is available to
monkeys and probably many other levels
as well but there might be a level which
is unique to humans this is the level of
nested symbolic structures in order to
describe the structures of language such
as this very simple phrase here those
gifted car factory workers you need
three structures you need parenthesis
you need to be able to say it's a Car
Factory and then there are workers in
this Factory it's not just car factory
workers as a sequence of words it's a
tree and the same applies to
mathematical patterns or mathematical
equations to musical patterns or to
theory of mind we need recursive
structures that are nested inside each
other so our hypothesis is that this may
be unique to the human brain and that
the human brain uses these three
structures to further compress the
information to discover some of the laws
symbolic laws perhaps that uh Joshua bjo
was talking about uh it uses nested
three structures to further compress the
information into extremely compact
Expressions I don't think I have time to
show you all of the Power of these ideas
so I'll refer you to this book how we
learn but I think this is a key idea for
how humans grow Concepts and I'm very
influenced by the work of Josh Tenon bom
and in this paper by Kemp and Tenon bom
they show how to build an algorithm that
can build new Concepts out of the
grammar generative grammar or smaller
ones and build Concepts such as the tree
of P
through this idea of a sort of language
of thought a grammar of thought so we're
starting to investigate whether this
actually occurs in humans and not in the
monkey using extremely simple paradigms
I will show you one you'll be surprised
by the simplicity so I hope you can see
the movie on the screen you can see that
there are eight locations here and this
is a test for young children we tell
them there's a fish which is hiding in
the spawns and U try to guess where he
going to go
okay so this is one trial learning I
hope you guessed where it's going to go
next everybody says he's going to go
here and then here and then here okay
you've guessed the pattern even before
it occurs try to do that with neural
networks you know it's not so easy this
is really very fast learning and what
we've shown is that in order to
understand this sort of learning you
need uh to assume some kind of language
of geometry you need to assume
Primitives for instance you need to
assume that the subject understand that
all of these diagonals they are all
symmetries on the fixed axis they're all
similar in a certain sense and so you
can anticipate that this is the next one
and then there will be this other
segment here um and you need a sort of
formula that expresses this repetitions
this formula is a bit complex but really
what it says is that there is a
repetition of four segments there's a
first segment second segment a third
segment and a fourth segment here and
you can build other shapes such as two
rectangles as long as there is
regularity you can find an expression
which is Compact and captures the
regularities that human captures well
we've done a lot of work with this I
won't bore you with all of the results
but just to say that our memory is
driven not by the length of the sequence
in fact all of the sequences we used
were always eight items but it's driven
by the minimal description length which
we call Cog complexity Al the lengths of
the shortest expression that can
compress the sequence and if you don't
have a language you don't have the
correct expression for these minimal
description legs it's not just slots
this idea of working memory as slots but
I think in humans it's not just slots
it's really compressing the
information um well we have a lot of
ongoing work at the moment to try to see
if this is true in the monkey as you can
see we did experiments with adults we
did experiment with preschoolers so it's
doesn't have much to do with being
trained in mathematics we even train
tested adults from the Amazon that have
very little access to education and
again found that you make more error for
sentences for phrases that sequences
that are more complex that is to say
they
have they are less compressible they
require a longer expression in order to
be described well this relationship we
don't find in the monkey at all in the
current work which is done by leing Wong
at The Institute of Neuroscience in
Shanghai after staying in my lab for
many years uh we see that monkeys do not
seem to care at all about the temporal
or geometrical regularities they just
tore the locations in working memory
they don't seem to care for the
structure of the transitions in order to
understand this language you need to
care very much about the nature of the
transitions much more than the
particular locations you need to be to
be able to understand that it's four
segments regardless of how they are
oriented for instance and monkeys don't
seem to do
that in very recent work which has just
been accepted in plus computational
biology we extend this approach to
auditory sequences let me test your
memory for sequences you think you could
remember this
[Laughter]
sequence okay this is eight I'm sorry 16
tones long 16 tones that can be a or b
high or low let me have you listen to it
[Laughter]
again okay I think you will agree that
it's almost impossible to remember at
least you will need many trials before
you can remember it now let's listen to
this one
you think you could repeat it the the
evidence is that you can maybe you'll
need two trials but not more because
this is highly regular and maybe here's
another
[Laughter]
one okay Your Capacity to remember these
sequences is again proportional to their
regularity we've tested this in two
different ways one is just to ask
subject for subjective complexity rating
so just rate the complexity as you feel
but the other is to ask for an objective
measure of complexity can you detect
whether there is a violation one of
these tones is wrong can you detected
and this is the percentage of detection
and combined also with the time that it
takes you to detect so remarkably the
very same measure of complexity that we
used for the geometric sequences can be
used for the auditory sequences it's a
cross modal notion of regularity the
only thing that you need to capture uh
what's Happening Here is a notion of
nested repetition there is repetition of
repetition of repetition and you can
compress the sequence by understanding
how this repetitions behave do you
switch from A to B or not once you have
that the length of the compress
compressed expression is a direct
predictor of how complex the sequence is
to remember so there is something in the
mind of humans that compresses the
information can monkeys do this at all
the evidence is that they count in fact
they may be missing some of the most
basic mechanism in order to integrate
information as we do in humans here's a
nice experiment by ding War when he was
in the lab um well the idea was we
should ask how do subjects really
understand the local Global sequence
that I showed you earlier so let me have
you listen to the
pattern okay I hope you perceive that
even though there is variation now
between the tones there's a lot of
regularity it's all always three
identical sounds and then there's a
different one can monkeys can monkeys
understand that do they have something
in mind just like us they would say it's
three tones X and then another tone y um
this seems to be a sort of minimal
expression that humans will use in order
to compress this information do monkeys
have this at all in order to test it we
had several violations you can change to
a new uh set of tones but still keep the
same rule so it's new example of the
same role or you can violate the number
you can have only two or maybe six items
or you can violate the sequence itself
you expect that the last one is going to
be different but it's not or you can
have double deviant double the violation
so it's the wrong number and also the
last item is not is not right we scan
monkeys and we scan humans during this
task it's a complex set of results while
I will summarize it very briefly this is
the activation to the violations in
number and this is the activation evoked
to the violation of sequences the last
item R and this is the intersection in
yellow you can see that the monkey has
both he has regions such as the int
paral cortex which we know cares about
number and reacts to number violations
and we find that in the human as well we
have a number sense ability to react to
number we also have responses to uh
violations of sequences in the monkey
you can see that in Green in particular
in inferior frontal cortex what we don't
have in the monkey is the areas in in
yellow in humans there is a whole set of
areas in inferior frontal gy Brokers
area here and in the psts in both
hemispheres that react to the violation
of both rules and that seem to encode a
single formula for the entire rule that
the monkey or the human has been
remembering and we really see this as a
strong dissociation humans show similar
pattern of activity for number sequence
change as if they the single
representation sorry about
that monkey show negative correlation so
if a voxel activates for number it does
not activate for sequence so monkeys
don't have the integrated
representation that we suggest is
present in humans and may be present in
fact around broker's area around the
inferior prefrontal cortex in several
areas of human prefrontal cortex we find
evidence for this integration according
to rules so monkeys May simply not be
able to integrate the information
consciously in the same way that we do
if I still have a few minutes I would
like to show you this in yet another
form which I think is a nice challenge
for artificial intelligence um this is a
drawing undoubtedly from humans not from
any ape not any not from any nonhuman
ape uh you can see the evidence of
drawing an animal but you can also see
geometrical shapes here a rectangle or a
series of dots is this unique to humans
indeed would a monkey ever understand
this sort of shape uh I like this joke
which appeared in the New Yorker here
you have these humans watching a hunting
scene and they say we have to record
this or no one's going to believe us
because what they see is not the actual
animal they see the shapes they see the
abstraction just like the artist that
Dre this in Las can we test this can we
test the idea that even when we look at
a very simple geometrical form we are
compressing it using its regularity we
are seeing regularities so this is the
work of Matas saer in the lab um what we
do here is we present you a very simple
display like this one here and you have
to spot the OD ball the outlier and I
hope you've seen that this one is the OD
ball because these are five rectangles
and this one is not a rectangle we do
this for every possible shape that is
displayed here from highly regular
square or rectangle to completely
irregular shapes that have no way to be
compressed rather than remembering the
specifics of the particular shape and we
find that regularity has a dramatic
effect on subject's ability to detect
the outlier this is another example here
it's a bit harder to detect the outlier
I hope for you until you find this one
as a displaced Corner we always displace
the corner this is important by the same
amount so it's not the amount of
displacement that counts it's the
regularity of the shape the more regular
the shape is the better you are so
you're super good at detecting
violations of a square or rectangle you
are very very poor at detecting
violations of an irregular shape and the
other ones they fall in between as a
function of the degree of regularity so
the humans may have this special notion
of a square as something which is
regular
particular it is a complete human
Universal I don't think I have time to
explain to you all the replications of
these effects in different paradigms
just subjective ratings again we have a
notion of introspection we have a
conscious introspection for the
complexity of these shapes we can even
present them as sequences it doesn't
have to be a shape so that's a little
bit of a challenge for let's say CNN's
uh convolutional neuron networks because
here the humans resist to the
presentation of the shapes as a sequence
of the Four Corners um but even
preschoolers or the HBA here adult
people who have very little access to
education they live in Namibia outside
of the normal Western environment they
still show this regularity effect so
it's a complete human Universal in our
hands at least doesn't depend on
education or at least uh it's present
already in a sort sort of simple form in
the absence of education so what about
monkeys we we were able to test it in
baboons this is a wonderful facility in
the south of France which Joel fago
running this facility where the baboons
can access this booth at any given time
and they can get video games this could
be a 2 in the morning you have a monkey
entering and he's recognized by the
system and he has access to a video game
and the video game is of course the one
that we designed uh we don't start with
the I'm getting
angry okay Mr Panda I'm closing so I
think you gu where I'm got getting
baboons can learn the outlier Tas they
can detect the ODB flower here they can
generalize to all of these stimuli so
they are able to learn the outb tars but
what they don't do is show a shape
regularity they are completely
from and you see that are essentially
flat they detect the outliers regardless
of whether it's a square or a or very
irregular shape which serves as a base
and we claim that CNN capture very well
in multiple regression the behaviors of
baboons but that they don't capture
what's happening in humans not at all
and that a completely different model is
needed in order to capture what's
happening in humans a model which lists
the internal properties of the shapes I
think I will just go to my
conclusion I think that human
consciousness is special of course there
is a conscious Global workspace in all
primates and perhaps in many other
animal species there's a beautiful paper
by Andreas Neer on corvids showing the
same sort of threshold and ignition in
uh the
crown I think we also share with many
other primates the same Core Concepts
for instance the concept of number of
object but also of space of person and
so on the basic concepts are there in
other primates but maybe according to
this new hypothesis only humans possess
an internal language of thought that
discretizes first of all the concepts
into mental tokens or symbols and
combines them recursively into mental
programs whose complexity determine
whether we're going to be able to
remember them or not and my argument is
that something happened during
omanization our brain architecture must
have changed in a way that facilitates
the acquisition of recursive languages
and this happens in several brain
networks language areas but also Mass
responsive areas or theory of Mind
regions giving rise to the extraordinary
complexity of human conscious
experiences this second part here what's
special to the human brain I would argue
is not yet well captured in artificial
intelligence it's more like system two
that Joshua benio was discussing so we
might have a discussion about that with
that I will leave you with these two
books and thank you very much for your
attention
hello hello
hello yes
yes thank you so much was an impressive
talk um as expected that was wonderful
mind-blowing a lot of beautiful data the
cognitive experiments are just so
mind-blowing and amazing um and it
nicely compliments um all of the work
we've been looking at that today
um we do have time for questions and we
have to take questions there just way so
many questions so I'm just going to pull
up he the questions and see those that
have been uploaded most and maybe we can
go through a few of them and again we'll
have time later in the panel so I'm
gonna ask first so the first question um
You probably see it also stand on the
ask question tab the first one is by uh
a Miller who's asking uh in the global
Network space in the gmw Theory does
Consciousness require um control
oriented interceptive uh inference um as
advocated by Anil in his talk this
morning so the way to incorporate
interceptive inference yeah I I don't
think so I I I think that there is a lot
but I I may not fully understand the
concept that Anil has been proposing but
I I I think the theory that I'm
proposing is that we can be conscious of
many different things and uh this does
not necessarily require um any sense of
self or any any notion of interception
so on all it requires is an internal
system for broadcasting information can
be very abstract so think of what you
are doing when you're doing mathematics
um but I'm not sure I fully understand
also the particular proposal here so
fair enough maybe we should discuss that
later yeah yeah we can get back to it so
um I'm G to take a question by um Andy
disra who's asking how do you address
the work of Michael pittz Steve Hillard
and others that claims that the p3b is
postperceptual rather than perception
actually per yeah I think it was a
little bit wrong to claim that one
particular wave which of course varies
from Paradigm to Paradigm also is can be
a universal signature of Consciousness
so so that has been clearly refuted I
think what is still clear is that if you
have a novel stimulus one which is not
expected then the PB is not a b sign of
consciousness
um but as soon as the stimulus becomes
habitual expected uh you don't
necessarily get it um and also if the
stimulus does not require a lot of
postprocessing as is being said in the
question then it can be severely reduced
that does not I think detract from the
fact that you have ignition the ignition
phenomenon is still present as I showed
I think especially in the new neural
recordings in the prefrontal cortex you
have very brief activation but still
crossing the prefrontal cortex and if
you don't need to hang on to it because
you're just passively looking then you
get it and then it's gone it flies by
basically so it will not create this
very Global wave that you can detect
from the outside which called the p3b
the p3b will be seen if you are
surprised or if you have to actively
report the
St um thank you I'm going to switch to a
question by Andrea brelli so Andrea is
asking um so from Mar he's asking
differences in movements be it sads or
micro sads may exist between conscious
so seen and unconscious unseen
processing of visual stimuli uh which
may lead to different responses for
example with Meg in the prefrontal
cortex starting like from 400
milliseconds so the question is would
you exclude such potential confounding
effects we typically do uh we typically
always record ey movements in Meg it's
also the case of course in the monkey
experiments and we can analyze show that
there is no detectable difference now
you could always argue that there are
you know micro Cades that are still
present of course below the resolution
of the particular scanner but I think
there are enough paradigms now that we
can exclude this interpretation in
particular in the auditory paradigms I
see no reason why there would be a
contamination with the
movements okay so maybe one last
question here before we move on later on
to our panel discussion this is a
question by Hikaru uh to jimura and
basically it relates to u to linking the
uh Global neural workspace to default
mode Network so question is what is the
core difference between uh the global
neural workspace and the default mode
Network especially the advantage of the
of the global neural workspace to
explain mechanisms of Consciousness or
awareness that's an interesting question
uh first of all I think that in science
it's often the case that we name same
things with different names and we see
the bridges later on so this could be a
case um however I think that the global
neuronal workspace is broader than the
particular default mode Network which
typically pointed out in some studies
for instance um you get a different
network within the global workspace you
get different topologies of the network
depending on the contents of what's
being accessed by the subject and
default mode Network seem to relate more
to verbal contents perhaps although it's
bilateral so in the right emisphere is
more than
that but we can also get slightly
different network if you think about
mathematical Concepts instance and then
it's a clearly different network so I
think that uh this relates to what I
said in the introduction there a style
of processing which is associated with
conscious processing but it's not
necessarily a fixed set of areas that
are always coming up when you're
conscious it's the style of activation
ignition the fact that the subset of
prefrontal neurons are being activated
and the others are being silenced which
tells us that the subject was conscious
of a piece of
information um awesome so I will take
one last question because this one's the
most outvoted one um so you can probably
see it um at the very top um of the list
uh so the question is in the global
neural workspace um an important role is
ascribed to the prefrontal cortex but
the question is what about the
hippocampus which sits on top of the
cortical sensory hierarchy and has
important roles in obviously Association
memory of course and space and time so
how how do you see hyppocampus
this is a great question and very
important one there is the hypoc campus
there is also the thalamic nuclei that
are connected with the cortex and um of
course in human we tend to study mostly
the cortical responses and also in the
monkey now that we have access to PFC
recordings um but I completely agree
with the notion of the question that
this is a this is a linked system and I
think it's often the case that what gets
recorded in episodic memory has to be
conscious first so uh I think there's a
sense in which it's highly likely that
what gets stored in the hypoc compus in
episodic memory is was first a cortical
content that was ignited and in this
sense that would be a very important
relation between the two it works also
in the opposite direction when you
access consciously a memory you can
search your memory and suddenly it pops
into your Consciousness this is ignition
it comes from the hypoc compus it
doesn't come from the external world but
it comes from the hypo campus being able
to replay and eventually ignite an
entire assembly in prefontal cortex and
related areas so once again this is not
a localist theory I think because it is
a global workspace it needs a
distributed system and I don't like uh
the idea of reducing it to just
prefrontal cortex I think it's very
likely that the hypoc compus plays an
important role now we know that if you
have a legion in the hypoc campus you
can still be conscious again this points
to the idea that this is a distributed
system it's not one node that will knock
it off but still dynamically these nodes
tend to come up together when they
activated great thank you so much Stan
for all these enlightening answers to
these questions and to the wonderful
talk once again um we could go on
forever with these questions there are
many more popping up but uh in the
interest of time and because we have the
panel uh to be able to continue this
discussion I think we will move on so
thanks once again so please everybody
join me in thanking s Doan for this
amazing keynote lecture at Main 2020 and
we will be closing this session in a few
maybe in about a minute or so before we
switch on to the next one which is going
to be the panel discussion um and just
one note because we are many people
meeting we cannot have the panel
discussion at least from a speaker
perspective in crowdcast you all stay on
crowdcast but we will be moving to zoom
and will be rebroadcast through
crowdcast so you don't have to worry
about anything just the speakers this is
a reminder to the speakers joining the
panel you now need to close your your uh
crowdcast window and and switch to the
zoom link that we sent you but for
everybody else just stick around
everything is going to continue
happening on uh crowdcast uh fingers
crossed everything goes well I hope so
thank you once again and one last
comment that I'd like to make this is
out there for the students newcomers of
the field and people who have heard a
lot about Consciousness this morning um
and who might not have the background
and find it interesting uh or who have
some background but would like to know
more um I would just like to point out
there's going to be um an introductory
uh lecture tomorrow morning because
tomorrow is our introductory courses
lectures uh of Main 20120 and there
there's one tomorrow uh which is going
to be uh given by Stephanie so Professor
Stephanie blam morz from mild who's been
working on Consciousness for quite a
while um and has a strong expertise in
the field so she will be giving a talk
on the introduction to um the basics of
studying uh Consciousness uh with
Neuroscience so the neuroscientific
approaches to the study of Consciousness
an introduction that's going to be uh
actually the opening lecture tomorrow
morning at um 8 or 8:20 I think it's
8:20 tomorrow morning so make sure you
don't miss that um uh and so that's all
I wanted to tell you right now um we'll
be closing the session and um meeting up
again in a couple of minutes for the
panel discussion and just to let you
know the panel disc discussion is going
to be when we start it uh you will see
there will be some questions that will
be sent in the poll so down at the
bottom you you'll see appearing a button
where you can press and we've prepared a
couple of questions because we want to
ask you make this more interactive so
there'll be two or three slightly
provocative or confusing questions about
Consciousness uh so as soon as you see
those question the poll appear please
answer those questions and we'll have a
look at at your answers thanks once
again and thank you to all the
speakers e